Guide to the Edward Raney papers, 1937-1969.
Edward Raney papers, 1937-1969
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Edward Raney papers, 1937-1969.
53-2-2391
Edward Cowden, Raney 1909-
15.1 cubic ft.
--
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Original field notes, correspondence, and subject files of Edward C. Raney and his students relating to the Raney Collection of Fishes and photographs, slides, and negatives pertaining to his work and personal life.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Ichthyologist, zoologist, fishery biologist, and professor at Cornell University.
Edward C. Raney was Cornell's ichthyologist in the Dept. of Conservation and later in the Division of Biological Sciences from 1936 to 1971. Upon his retirement from Cornell, Raney did consulting work for Ichthyological Associates, his environmental consulting firm in Ithaca.
The Raney collection is used for basic research on the relationships and life histories of fresh water and ocean fish in New York State and other areas, particularly the Northeast. It contains the holotypes of 39 species of North American fishes and 228 lots of secondary typ material as well as an historical series of specimens collected from the same geographic locations through much of the last century.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Original field notes, correspondence, and subject files of Edward C. Raney and his students relating to the Raney Collection of Fishes and photographs, slides, and negatives pertaining to his work and personal life.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Raney, Edward Cowden,1909-; Cornell University.Division of Biological Sciences.Dept. of Ecology and Systematics.; Icthyological Associates.
Subjects:
Fishes--Collection and preservation.; Fishes--Classification.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Negatives.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Field notebooks and correspondence (Box 1 & 2)
  - Correspondence A-S, 1935-1950 (Box 3, Folder 1-54)
  - (Box 4, Folder 1-36)
    - Correspondence S-Z, 1935-1950
    - Correspondence A-K, 1950-1955
  - (Box 5, Folder 1-41)
    - Correspondence L-Z, 1950-1955
    - Correspondence A, 1954-1961
  - Correspondence A-G, 1954-1961 (Box 6, Folder 1-28)
  - Correspondence H-R, 1954-1961 (Box 7, Folder 1-37)
  - (Box 8, Folder 1-35)
    - Correspondence R-Z, 1954-1961
    - Correspondence A-B, 1965-1969
  - Correspondence C-S, 1965-1969 (Box 9, Folder 1-38)
  - Correspondence S-Z, 1965-1969 (Box 10, Folder 1-81)
  - Correspondence A-Z, 1958-1976 (Box 13)
- Series II: Subject Files
  - A-Catostomidae Moxostoma Pappillosum, 1953 (Box 10)
  - C-H: Catostomidae Moxostoma Poecilurum to Haplomi (Box 11, Folder 1-94)
  - Synentognathi- Key to Western Atlantic Belonidae to Percidae Hadropterus Notogrammus, 1942-1949 (Box 12, Folder 1-64)
  - P-T: Percidae Hadropterus Nigrofasciatus (1954-1955) \ Toad Recoveries (1940-1949), (1954-1955) \ (1940-1949) (Box 13, Folder 1-61)
- Series III: Slides/Negatives and Field Notebooks
  - Field notebooks and correspondence (Box 1 & 2)
  - Slides, negatives, field notebooks, maps with notations (Box 14 & 15)
  - Photos, correspondence and drafts of Hadropterus Crassus, 1940s-1960s (Box 16)
  - Photo of the 31st annual meeting of the American Society of Ichthydogists and Herpetologists- Chicago, 1951 (Box 41, Folder Oversize folder)